Guide to the New York Women's Culinary Alliance Archive 1982-2010 MSS.279
Fales Library and Special Collections
New York Women's Culinary Alliance Archive
1982-2010
Fales Library and Special Collections
New York Women's Culinary Alliance
MSS.279
3 Linear Feet in 3 boxes
11.8 Gigabytes in 15 files
1 Betacam
The New York Women's Culinary Alliance, founded in 1981, fosters networking, education, and cooperation for women in the culinary and beverage fields in the New York metro area. Early founders inlcude Sara Moulton and Maria Reuge, and right from the start its members included well known authors, caterers, chefs, cooking school teachers, editors, food writers, marketers, photographers, and stylists. The Archive includes records of the organization's founding, meeting notes, membership directories, newsletters, and reports on activities and events. There is also a video of "Moulton Visuals".
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Provenance
The New York Women's Culinary Alliance Archive was donated to NYU's Fales Library & Special Collections in 2010.
Arrangement
The New York Women's Culinary Alliance Archive is sorted into two series:
Series I: Organizational Records The materials are arranged alphabetically. There is one video element, which is at the end of the series.
Series II: Oral Histories
Historical Note
The New York Women's Culinary Alliance, founded in 1981, fosters networking, education, and cooperation for women in the culinary and beverage fields in the New York metro area. The Alliance provides members with continuing education opportunities by sponsoring ongoing food and wine tastings, hands-on workshops, field trips, and business-related seminars. They also support the preservation and sharing of culinary information through member-generated programs. The Alliance assumes a dynamic role in community affairs, particularly through outreach programs and fund-raising for women's health and nutrition issues, and work with adults and children in need to teach them the basics of nutrition, food buying, and healthful meal preparation.
The Alliance came into being as the food world was turning toward more sophisticated flavors, seasonal cooking, and artisanal foods. The Alliance quickly became a forum for dozens of women whose careers centered upon food and beverages, encouraging them to meet, share expertise, and drive new directions in the food world. Early founders inlcude Sara Moulton and Maria Reuge, and right from the start its members included well known authors, caterers, chefs, cooking school teachers, editors, food writers, marketers, photographers, and stylists. Members of the Alliance have produced dozens of best-selling cookbooks, hosted nationally televised cooking shows, and produced or edited content for the country's leading magazines and newspapers.
Sources:
Excerpt from press release of NYU's acquisition of the archive
New York Women's Culinary Alliance wesbite (www.nywca.org)
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes records of the organization's founding, meeting notes, membership directories, newsletters, and reports on activities and events. There is also a video of "Moulton Visuals".
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Culinary industry.; Food habits -- New York (State) -- New York; Women in the food industry.; Food industry and trade |z New York (State) |z New York; New York Women's Culinary Alliance; Moulton, Sara, 1952-
- Series I: Organizational Records
  - Alliance bylaw chances, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anniversary Program, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beard Foundation, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Binders - newsletters, website, etc., Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board Meetings, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board Meetings, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board Meetings, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board Meetings, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board Meetings, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board Meetings, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board Meetings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board Meetings, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board Meetings, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board Meetings, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board Meetings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board Meetings, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board Meetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board Meetings, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Board Meetings, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Board Meetings, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Budgets, 1998-2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - California Table Grape Commission - fundraiser, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cancer fighting Food - fundraiser, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Contracts - space rental, 1993-2005 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cooking with Kids - insert, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Culinary Alliance - "Facts to File", "Provisionally Speaking", 1980's (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Days of Taste - Girls Give Back, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dinner Party Project (Days of Taste), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Directory, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - For the Love of Chocolate (fundraiser for City Harvest) - Event Info, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - For the Love of Chocolate (fundraiser for City Harvest) - Exhibitor responses, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - For the Love of Chocolate (fundraiser for City Harvest) - loose items, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - For the Love of Chocolate (fundraiser for City Harvest) - Silent Auction, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - For the Love of Chocolate (fundraiser for City Harvest) - Sponsorship info, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Honey fundraiser, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Invitations, 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Invitation - 20th Anniversary, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Loose items, Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Member Survey - Pranses Research Services report, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Member Survey - Pranses Research Services report, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Member Survey - Pranses Research Services report, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Membership, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Membership Directories, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Membership Directories, 1995-2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Membership Directories, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Membership Directories, 2005-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Membership Directories, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Membership Renewal Set, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Nancy Jessup - tax letter, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Potato Board - fundraiser, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New York Children's Health Project, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newsletter redesign, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Newsletters, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Newsletters, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Newsletters, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Newsletters, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Newsletters, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Newsletters, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Newsletters, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Newsletters, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Newsletters, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Newsletters, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Newsletters, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Newsletters, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Newsletters, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Newsletters - notes, etc., Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Newsletters - c/o Shari Lyn Bayer, Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Newsletters - c/o Suzanne Fass, Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - NYWCA Artwork Logo, Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - NYWCA Board elections, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - NYWCA Introduction, Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Party Planning Kit and Invitations, Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Potlucks, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Potlucks, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Press Profile, Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Printing, Undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Printing - Cara International, Undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Program kit, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Program kit, Undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Program letters to members, Undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Publicity and Tear sheets, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Receipt books (carbon copies), Undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Share-a-Walk, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Thank You and Fundraising letters, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Website, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Website Alliance, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Wine Auction - Marion Gorman, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Wine and Ethnic Food Pairing with ICE, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Women and Money survey, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Women and Money survey, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Betacam Video - "Moulton Visuals", c. 1980 - 1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
- Series II: Oral Histories, 2013; 15 media elements
  Scope and Content
  Oral histories conducted by Carol Durst-Wertheim with members of NYWCA. Directed by Sarah Gurfield.
  - Introduction and credits, FA_MSS_279_ER_1; 1 media elements
  - Dana Jacobi, FA_MSS_279_ER_2; 1 media elements 16 minutes, 23 seconds
    General
    Interview is audio only.
  - Delores Custer, FA_MSS_279_ER_3; 1 media elements
  - Delores Custer and Joanne Lamb Hayes, FA_MSS_279_ER_4; 1 media elements
  - Diana Sturgis, FA_MSS_279_ER_5; 1 media elements
  - Georgia Downward, FA_MSS_279_ER_6; 1 media elements
  - Jean Anderson, FA_MSS_279_ER_7; 1 media elements
  - Maira Reuge, FA_MSS_279_ER_8
  - Mary Cleaver, FA_MSS_279_ER_9
  - Michele Scicolone, FA_MSS_279_ER_10
  - Miriam Rubin, FA_MSS_279_ER_11
  - Nancy Jessup, FA_MSS_279_ER_12
  - Ruth Cousineau, FA_MSS_279_ER_13
  - Sandy Gluck, FA_MSS_279_ER_14
  - Sara Moulton, FA_MSS_279_ER_15